RG 062:054, Town of Glastonbury
Glastonbury Records, Inventory of Town of
Connecticut State Library
Town of Glastonbury records
1720-1909
Connecticut State Library
Glastonbury (Conn.)
27.5 cubic feet
Administrative, poor relief, land, court and justice of hte peace, law enforcement, military, vital, school, voting, and tax records.
RG062_054
T000317
Historical Note
The area of Connecticut known as Glastonbury was settled by members of a church from Watertown, Massachusetts, and originally formed part of Wethersfield. In 1690, Glastonbury petitioned the General Assembly to establish a separate community and a separate church Society. Incorporation occurred three years later, when the community settled a minister.
In the 18th century, Glastonbury was noted for its shipbuilding and its trade in lumber. Three streams-Salmon, Hubbard and Roaring Brook-powered saw mills that produced clapboards and pipe staves for export to New York, the southern colonies and the West Indies. Other industries located along those streams included iron foundries run by the Hunt, Hodge and Stevens families; brick manufactories; a glass works; a powder mill; and textile mills. The Hartford Manufacturing Company and Wassuc Co. produced cotton goods while Roaring Brook and Eagle Mills produced woolens. In the 1850s, the Curtis family established the Curtisville Company that produced silver-plated hollow ware. The majority of the 18th and 19th century residents made their living from farming. Between 1850 to 1900, Glastonbury's growth slowed considerably and it became a semi-rural agricultural community with a few sizeable industries. In the 21st century, the town is home to individuals who commute to Hartford and surrounding businesses. It is also noted for its variety of orchards and fruit farms.
In 1870, the residents voted to change the spelling of their town from Glastenbury to Glastonbury to emulate the English town of the same name.
Scope and Content
Two people employed under the W.P.A. program arranged the records in groups of like material organized by date. The archivist has retained that rough organization and divided the materials into ten Series. Administrative records, 1762-1904, include minutes of town meetings, 1804-1818, 1822, 1829; petitions for town meetings, for building roads, and against a "taverner", 1824-1896; appointments of overseers, 1782-1842 who helped failing farmers become self-sustaining; contracts for building roads, 1825-1841, 1891-1904; and bills, receipts and accounts, 1806-1896. Selectmen's correspondence, 1824-1896, contains some letters regarding a ferry across the Connecticut River and some relating to care of the poor. Of particular note among the administrative records are votes relating to the State Constitutional Convention in 1818, and a contract for building a new Town House in 1840. Apprenticeship indentures, 1779-1822, include those in which the town bound out poor boys and girls, some to learn a trade and others to work as servants. Among the bills of sale are two documents, 1753, 1860, relating to the sale of interests in sailing vessels. There are also accounts of timber found or "taken afloat", 1818-1841.
From earliest settlement into the 19th century, New England towns refused to provide care for poor individuals who came from other municipalities. Travelers often carried a certificate indicating their residence. Poor individuals were auctioned to the lowest bidder who then contracted to care for these people, usually for a year at a time. These practices are documented in Series 2, Poor Relief Records, 1771-1791, 1839. In addition to the certificates and contracts, this series encompasses inventories of bedding and clothing of the poor, 1821-1838; correspondence with neighboring town governments, 1822-1829; and bills and accounts for keeping the poor, 1816-1824, 1896, including bills from the Hartford Manufacturing Company for fabric. Of note in these records are bills for digging a grave and building a coffin for Cato Ward, "Negro", in 1822.
Series 3 consists of land records, namely deeds, 1720-1901; boundary and road surveys, 1722-1826; and a ca. 1878 grantor index for land transactions between 1695-1878. Records of the county, state and local courts and of Justices of the Peace in Series 4 include General Assembly appointments of Justices, 1842-1847; and probate records from several estates handled by Attorney William Goslee. The bulk of the court records consist of justice files, which include writs that order the sheriff to attach an individual's goods or estate and/or summon a defendant to court, and "confest" judgments, 1730-1887. In a confessed judgment, a defendant agreed to the charge against him and made restitution without attending court. These documents are arranged by date of the judgment. The writs
were primarily issued in cases involving unpaid debts, but also include cases of assault, defamation, trespass, breach of contract, theft, shooting a hog, and support for a bastard child. A note about the hearing and the judgment for each case is usually found on the verso of the writ. For cases involving unpaid debts, the writs are often accompanied by the original promissory note signed by the defendant. Justice files are arranged by the date on the original writ or complaint with later documents following.
Law enforcement records in Series 5 consist of records of loose livestock, 1783-1816, which were reported to the constable. Men who served in the militia were often given an abatement on their taxes. Series 6 encompasses certificates proving military service that were sent to the tax assessor, lists of enlisted men, and certificates awarding a leave of absence, 1813-1825, 1841; an account for supplies, n.d.; lists of volunteers for 1863; and Caroline Wright's war claim, 1892. Certificates of military service can also be found among the tax records.
Marriage certificates written by the minister who conducted the ceremony, 1820-1855, are arranged in Series 7. Series 8, School Records, 1806-1909, includes financial records, calls for meetings, minutes, Board of School visitors' certifications, and bills for the South Glastonbury School Society, the Fourth School District, Sixth School District, and School District No. 2.
Voting Records, 1784-1890, in Series 9, include reports to the Secretary of the State on electors' votes for the Governor, Lieutenant Governor, Secretary of the State, Treasurer, Assistants, Jurymen, and members of Congress. Local elections documented in this series consist of Inspectors of Fish, Lumber and Flour; and nominations for men considered suitable to keep houses of entertainment. Results of the town's voting in the Presidential election of 1820 are included in these records. Several volumes listing the town's electors apparently maintained by attorney William S. Goslee, contained loose papers inside the front and back covers. These relate to his private law practice and to the activities of the town treasurer. They have been arranged in folders following the volumes in which they were found.
The final Series is comprised of tax records, the bulk of which are individual lists. These lists came bundled together and tied with string. The bundles did not appear to represent a different tax assessor or a different section of town, so for ease of use they were arranged by year and then alphabetically. The spelling of the last names changed. For example, Wier was also spelled Wire, but by 1865, it was consistently spelled Weir. A note of caution to researchers-sometimes an assessor used the same form for several years, particularly if a person's personal and real estate did not change. The latest year found on the form, often on the verso, was used as the date of record.
Additional records in this Series include lists of polls and minors, 1813-1818; rate books and assessors' lists, 1829-1885; abatements; and assessments for particular items such as carriages and on specific occupations including mechanics, physicians and attorneys, 1779-1838. Of particular interest are certificates obtained by members of "dissenting" churches to release them from having to pay taxes to support the Congregational minister, 1817-1819.
Arrangement
Series 1. Administrative Records (1762-1904) contain selectmen's records, including minutes of town meetings, petitions, contracts, indentures, financial records and correspondence.
Series 2. Poor Relief Records (1771-1896) contain residency certificates, inventories of bedding and clothing of the poor, correspondence with neighboring town governments, and bills and accounts.
Series 3. Land Records (1720-1901) contain deeds, boundary and road surveys, and grantor index.
Series 4. Court and Justice of the Peace Records (1730-1891) contain appointments of justices, writs, summonses, confessed judgments, and probate records for estates handled by attorney William S. Goslee.
Series 5. Law Enforcement Records (1783-1816) contain records of lost livestock.
Series 6. Military Records (1813-1895) contain certificates of service, lists of enlisted men, leaves of absence certificates, an account for supplies, a list of volunteers for 1863, and widow's war claim.
Series 7. Vital Records (1820-1855) contain marriage certificates.
Series 8. School Records (1806-1909) contain financial records, calls for meetings, minutes, and Board of School Visitors' certifications.
Series 9. Voting Records (1784-1890) lists of electors, freemen's oaths, vote returns and votes related to the State Constitution.
Series 10. Tax Records (1779-1895) contain lists of polls and minors, certificates of church membership, rate books, abatements, special assessments, and individual tax lists. See container list.
Related Material
Additional primary materials relating to Glastonbury can be found in the classified archives 974.62 G46, and in Record Group 69, in Series 24, the Papers of William S. Goslee, 1815-1892, and in Series 83, Goslee Collection, 1795-1905. Specific records from these collections that complement those described in the container list are noted under the appropriate Series. The classified archives include church and school records, and account books kept by Glastonbury citizens. William Goslee's papers include court and estate papers, church records, materials concerning the boundary dispute between Wethersfield and Glastonbury, and records from his legal practice. The Goslee Collection contains financial records, deeds, court and estate papers, and correspondence. Descriptions of these materials can also be found in the collection file for Glastonbury.
The library of the Glastonbury Historical Society also holds a sizeable collection of primary documents including business ledgers related to shipbuilding and the merchant trade, whaling logs, diaries, poll and tax records, a large collection of photographs, and maps, including a 1776 map of New England.
Researchers may also wish to consult two published histories of the town:
Glastonbury: From Settlement to Suburb, by Marjorie G. McNulty (Historical Society of Glastonbury, 1975 )
, and
Glastenbury for Two Hundred Years: a Centennial Discourse, May 18th 1853, by Alonzo B. Chapin (Hartford: Case, Tiffany & Co., 1853 )
.
Index Terms
Alternate Creators:
Connecticut. Justice of the Peace (Glastonbury)
Subjects:
Public welfare -- Connecticut -- Glastonbury; Deeds -- Connecticut -- Glasontonbury; Justices of the peace -- Connecticut -- Glasontonbury; Writs -- Connecticut -- Glasontonbury; Soldiers -- Connecticut -- Glasontonbury; Elections -- Connecticut -- Glasontonbury -- Statistics; Voting -- Connecticut -- Glasontonbury -- Statistics; Voting registers -- Connecticut -- Glasontonbury; Tax assessment -- Connecticut -- Glasontonbury -- Registers; Taxation -- Connecticut -- Glasontonbury -- Registers; Local taxation -- Connecticut -- Glasontonbury -- Registers; Property tax -- Connecticut -- Glasontonbury -- Registers; Schools -- Connecticut -- Glasontonbury -- History -- Sources
Places:
Glastonbury (Conn.) -- Records and correspondence; Glastonbury (Conn.) -- Statistics, Vital
Document Types:
Administrative records; Civil court records; Deeds; Election returns; Military records; Probate records; School records; Tax records; Vital records; Voters' lists
Restrictions on Access
Some records are restricted because of their fragile condition. Copies of these documents replace the originals, which are housed separately. In addition, an apprenticeship indenture naming a "mulatto or Indian boy" has been copied and the original housed separately.
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Container List
- Series 1. Administrative Records, 1762-1904
  Related material
  Additional bills, receipts and accounts with the town, 1799-1809, can be found in the classified archives.
  - Minutes of town meetings, 1804-1818, 1822, 1829 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Town votes relating to the state constitutional convention, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Petitions, 1824-1896 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Apprenticeship indentures, 1779-1822 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Contract for building the Town House, 1840 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Town officers' bonds, 1842, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Appointments of overseers, 1782-1842 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Copy of resolution from the General Assembly, 1762 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Petition to the General Assembly, 1816 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Contracts, 1833 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bills of sale, 1807, 1821, 1860, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bonds and agreements, 1762, 1860, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Accounts of timber found or "taken afloat", 1818-1841 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Selectmen's correspondence regarding a ferry, 1824, 1829 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Selectmen's correspondence, some relating to care of the poor, 1891-1896 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Contracts for building roads, 1825-1841, 1891-1904 (Box 1, Folder 17-23)
  - Notices to treasurer of interest accrued on town accounts, 1895-1896 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Bills, receipts and accounts, 1806-1815 (Box 1, Folder 25-35)
  - Bills, receipts and accounts, 1815-1896 (Box 2, Folder 36-82)
- Series 2. Poor Relief Records, 1771-1896
  - Certificates of residency, 1771-1791, 1839 (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
  - Contracts for keeping the poor, 1820-1848 (Box 3, Folder 5-7)
  - Affidavit of birth and residence, 1822 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - List of poor, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Inventories of bedding and clothing of poor, 1821-1838 (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
  - Correspondence, 1822-1829 (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
  - Town accounts for keeping poor, 1821-1824 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Bills for digging grave and building coffin for Cato Ward, "Negro", 1822 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Bills from other towns and from Glastonbury residents for keeping poor, 1816-1824, 1896 (Box 3, Folder 15-19)
- Series 3. Land Records, 1720-1901
  Additional Glastonbury deeds can be found in Record Group 69, Series 83, Goslee Collection. Material concerning the Wethersfield-Glastonbury boundary dispute is in Record Group 69, Series 24.
  - Deeds, 1720-1759 (Box 3, Folder 1-13)
  - Deeds, 1760-1802 (Box 4, Folder 14-33)
  - Deeds, 1803-1815 (Box 5, Folder 34-55)
  - Deeds, 1816-1829 (Box 6, Folder 56-76)
  - Deeds, 1830-1901 (Box 7, Folder 77-84)
  - Boundary and road surveys, 1722-1826 (Box 7, Folder 85-89)
  - Grantor index for deeds executed between 1695-1878, circa 1878; 9 volumes (Box 52)
- Series 4. Court and Justice of the Peace Records, 1730-1891
  Additional court and estate records maintained by William Goslee, 1865-1892, are contained in Record Group 69, Series 24. Other Goslee family material is contained in Record Group 69, Series 83, Goslee Collection.
  - General Assembly appointments of Justices of the Peace, 1842-1847 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Justice files, 1730-1787 (Box 7, Folder 2-15)
  - Justice files and "confest" judgments, 1788-1795 (Box 8, Folder 16-37)
  - Justice files and "confest" judgments, 1796-1801 (Box 9, Folder 38-62)
  - Justice files and "confest" judgments, 1802-1808 (Box 10, Folder 63-86)
  - Justice files and "confest" judgments, 1814-1839 (Box 11, Folder 87-116)
  - Probate records, 1754-1771, 1878-1890 (Box 12, Folder 117)
  - Andrews Estate records, William Goslee, attorney, 1891 (Box 12, Folder 118)
  - Sarah Morley Estate, settled by the town, 1822 (Box 12, Folder 119)
  - Phelps Estate records, William Goslee, attorney, 1890-1891 (Box 12, Folder 120-121)
  - Julia Smith et al. vs. Andrews & Hardin, William Goslee, Attorney, 1874-1880 (Box 12, Folder 122-124)
  - Deposition, 1783 (Box 12, Folder 125)
- Series 5. Law Enforcement Records, 1783-1816
  - Constable's records concerning loose livestock, 1783, 1800, 1816 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Series 6. Military Records, 1813-1895
  - Certificates of service and leaves of absence, lists of enlisted men, 1813-1825, 1841, undated (Box 12, Folder 1-6)
  - Account for supplies, amounts due to individual soldiers, undated (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - List of volunteers, 1863 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Form for listing children of deceased soldiers, circa 1895 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Caroline Wright's war claim, 1892 (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Series 7. Vital Records, 1820-1855
  - Marriage certificates, 1820-1855 (Box 12, Folder 1-14)
- Series 8. School Records, 1806-1909
  Note: Additional school records, including a return of scholars from the 5th District, August 1830, minutes of the First School Society, 1819-1844, and records from the 16th District, 1866-1909, can be found in the classified archives. Records from the Glastonbury Academy, 1870-1885, are contained in Record Group 69, Series 24, Papers of William S. Goslee.
  - South Glastonbury School Society financial records and calls for meetings, 1846-1854 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Minutes of 16th School District meetings, 1856-1909; 1 volume (Box 12)
  - School District No. 2 bills, 1876-1877 (Box 13, Folder 2-3)
  - Board of School Visitors certifications, 1895-1896 (Box 13, Folder 4-7)
  - Assorted bills, 1806, 1895-1896, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
- Series 9. Voting Records, 1784-1890
  - Votes of the Civil Authority for jurymen and inspectors, 1784-1830 (Box 13, Folder 1-6)
  - Freemen's Oaths, 1792-1818 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Votes of freemen's meetings, 1804-1818, undated (Box 13, Folder 8-12)
  - Votes related to the State Constitution, 1818, 1838-1847 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Vote reports of electors, 1819-1844 (Box 13, Folder 14-23)
  - Vote reports of electors, 1845-1864 (Box 14, Folder 24-27)
  - Vote reports found unopened, 1828-1845 (Box 14, Folder 28-29)
  - Blank vote reports, undated (Box 14, Folder 30)
  - "Canvass" of voters, volume 1, 1868 (Box 14)
  - List of electors (kept by William Goslee), volume 2, 1879 October 6 (Box 14)
  - List of electors, volume 3, 1879 November 4 (Box 14)
  - List of electors, volume 4, 1880 October 4 (Box 14)
  - List of electors, volume 5, 1880 November 2 (Box 14)
  - Items removed from volume 5 (Box 14, Folder 31)
  - List of electors, volume 6, 1881 November 8 (Box 14)
  - List of electors, volume 7, 1882 (Box 14)
  - List of electors, volume 8, 1883 (Box 14)
  - List of electors, volume 9, 1885 (Box 14)
  - Items removed from volume 9 (Box 14, Folder 32)
  - List of electors, volume 10, 1889 (Box 14)
  - Items removed from volume 10 (Box 14, Folder 33-34)
  - List of electors, volume 11, 1890 (Box 15)
  - Items removed from volume 11 (Box 15, Folder 35)
- Series 10. Tax Records, 1779-1895
  Note: Rate books for 1730, 1768, 1801 and 1817 can be found in classified archives.
  - Lists of polls and minors, 1813-1818 (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
  - Certificates of church membership, 1817-1819 (Box 15, Folder 3-5)
  - Collector's account, 1815-1819 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Assorted documents, including list of districts, information about bank stock holders, and a military commutation tax notice, 1817-1895 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Rate book, volume 1, 1829 (Box 15)
  - Rate book, assessors' lists, 1833, 1837, undated (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Rate book, volume 2, 1871-1874 (Box 15)
  - Rate book, volume 3, 1881 (Box 15)
  - Rate book, volume 4, 1885 (Box 15)
  - Abatements and assessments, 1779-1838 (Box 16, Folder 9-33)
  - List of liens, undated (Box 16, Folder 34)
  - Individual tax lists (Box 16)
    - A-F, 1820 (Box 16, Folder 35-44)
    - G-V, 1820 (Box 17, Folder 45-69)
    - W, non-resident, 1820 (Box 18, Folder 70-76)
    - 1821 (Box 18, Folder 77-101)
      Additional tax lists for 1821 can be found in the classified archives.
    - 1824 (Box 18, Folder 102-104)
    - A-C, 1830 (Box 18, Folder 105-106)
    - D-W, 1830 (Box 19, Folder 107-130)
    - A-Har, 1831 (Box 19, Folder 131-137)
    - Hol-Wr, 1831 (Box 20, Folder 138-151)
    - 1832 (Box 20, Folder 152-166)
    - 1833 (Box 21, Folder 167-172)
    - 1834 (Box 21, Folder 173-183)
    - 1835 (Box 21, Folder 184-191)
    - B-H, 1836 (Box 21, Folder 192-195)
    - L-W, 1836 (Box 22, Folder 195-198)
    - A-W, 1837 (Box 22, Folder 199-217)
    - A-Hollister, L, 1838 (Box 22, Folder 218-223)
    - Hollister, N-W, 1838 (Box 23, Folder 224-231)
    - A-Se, 1839 (Box 23, Folder 232-252)
    - Sh-W, 1839 (Box 24, Folder 253-259)
    - A-W, 1840 (Box 24, Folder 260-280)
    - A-W, 1841 (Box 25, Folder 281-296)
    - 1841 list for 1842 School Tax (Box 25, Folder 297-299)
    - A-W, 1842 (Box 25, Folder 300-304)
    - A-F, 1843 (Box 25, Folder 305-308)
    - G-W, 1843 (Box 26, Folder 309-322)
    - A-W, 1844 (Box 26, Folder 323-327)
    - A-W, 1846 (Box 26, Folder 328-330)
    - School District list, A-W, 1846 (Box 26, Folder 331-333)
    - A-Ca, 1847 (Box 26, Folder 334-335)
    - Ch-W, 1847 (Box 27, Folder 336-351)
    - Fourth School District, Second School Society, 1847 (Box 27, Folder 352)
    - Letters to assessors, 1848 (Box 27, Folder 353)
    - B-W, 1848 (Box 27, Folder 354-356)
    - A-W, 1849 (Box 28, Folder 357-373)
    - A-C, 1850 (Box 28, Folder 374-383)
    - D-Po, 1850 (Box 29, Folder 384-411)
    - Pr-W, 1850 (Box 30, Folder 412-430)
    - A-L, 1851 (Box 30, Folder 431-439)
    - M-W, 1851 (Box 31, Folder 440-446)
    - A-Hubbard, 1852 (Box 31, Folder 447-470)
    - Hunt-W, 1852 (Box 32, Folder 471-493)
    - A-Cor, 1853 (Box 32, Folder 494-500)
    - Cov-Risley, 1853 (Box 33, Folder 501-528)
    - Ro-W, 1853 (Box 34, Folder 529-544)
    - A-Ma, 1854 (Box 34, Folder 545-562)
    - Me-W, 1854 (Box 35, Folder 562-573)
    - A-L, 1855 (Box 35, Folder 574-597)
    - M-W, 1855 (Box 36, Folder 598-613)
    - A-Hale, 1856 (Box 36, Folder 614-629)
    - Hali-W, 1856 (Box 37, Folder 630-629)
    - A-H, 1857 (Box 37, Folder 652-660)
    - J-W, 1857 (Box 38, Folder 661-668)
    - A-Hills, 1858 (Box 38, Folder 669-689)
    - Hod-Wick, 1858 (Box 39, Folder 690-721)
    - Wier-Wy, 1858 (Box 40, Folder 722-724)
    - A-Me, 1859 (Box 40, Folder 725-755)
    - Mi-W, 1859 (Box 41, Folder 756-776)
    - A-Cha, 1860 (Box 41, Folder 777-783)
    - Chi-Sa, 1860 (Box 42, Folder 784-812)
    - Se-W, 1860 (Box 43, Folder 813-826)
    - Individual tax lists, non-residents, 1860 (Box 43, Folder 827)
    - A-Ga, 1861 (Box 43, Folder 828-841)
    - Gi-Tay, 1861 (Box 44, Folder 842-875)
    - Th-W, 1861 (Box 45, Folder 876-884)
    - Non-residents, 1861 (Box 45, Folder 885-886)
    - A-Ste, 1862 (Box 45, Folder 887-904)
    - Sto-W, 1862 (Box 46, Folder 905-909)
    - Non-resident, 1862 (Box 46, Folder 910)
    - A-W, 1863 (Box 46, Folder 911-937)
    - A-House, 1864 (Box 47, Folder 938-968)
    - How-Whe, 1864 (Box 48, Folder 969-997)
    - Wi-Wr, 1864 (Box 49, Folder 998-999)
    - Non-resident, 1864 (Box 49, Folder 1000)
    - A-Hodge, 1865 (Box 49, Folder 1001-1023)
    - Holl-Stri, 1865 (Box 50, Folder 1024-1048)
    - Stro-W, 1865 (Box 51, Folder 1049-1059)
    - Non-resident, 1865 (Box 51, Folder 1060-1062)
    - 1866 (Box 51, Folder 1063)
- Oversize materials
  - Oversize materials (Box 53)
- Restricted materials
  - Restricted materials (Box 54)